<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The advise of a sonne, novv professing the religion established in the present Church of England, to his deare mother, yet a Roman Catholike</title>
            <author>Hungerford, Anthony, Sir, 1564-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13971.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 864:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The advise of a sonne, novv professing the religion established in the present Church of England, to his deare mother, yet a Roman Catholike</title>
                  <author>Hungerford, Anthony, Sir, 1564-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Sir Anthony Hungerford.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 155.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 155 on UMI microfilm reel 864.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ADVISE OF A SONNE, NOVV PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FESSING THE RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON ESTABLISHED IN the preſent Church of England, <hi>to his deare Mother, yet a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholike.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes, Printer to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>verſitie.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15667:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15667:2"/>
            <head>THE ADVISE OF A SONNE VNTO HIS MOTHER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing it hath pleaſed God to appoint you the meane of my being in the world, by whoſe holy ordinance you may iuſtly chalenge, as of your right fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, all ſincere affection, dutie, and obſervation; and beſides the bond of Nature, my obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion being much encreaſed by your moſt louing, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued care of me, even from my childhood, it is now my part (and that vnder perill of a curſe, if I neglect it) by all meanes I may to yeeld comforts to your yeares, and from my hart and ſoule to wiſh, that when your temporarie daies on earth ſhal end, you may by the mercy of God take poſſeſſion of the eternall ioyes of heaven. I know (and haue wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of this, ſo many as haue knowne you) that your intentions haue ever aimed at this mark, your life and actions haue beene a rare patterne to your ſexe, alwaies well declaring your devotion &amp; zeale to the ſervice of God: The which being the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall end of our creation (howſoever the generalitie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15667:3"/>now in this ſtate of corruption, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported with the cares, the pleaſures, and enticements of this life, lay it not to the heart) it is without queſtion a bleſſing incomparable (whereof none can judge, but they that feele it) when God of his meere mercie by his holy Spirit, ſhal moue the heart of a ſinful creature, who before delighted only in the way of his owne deſtruction, ſincerely to ſeeke and ſerue him: for this we may build vpon, as a truth that muſt admit no queſtion, that never any ſhall haue their place in heaven, whoſe hearts by grace haue not beene true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued to this duty heere on earth. Since then the time of this life is the moment wherevpon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth etermitie of weale or woe, it behooveth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian that deſires ſalvation, ſeriouſly to conſider of the way he walkes in; eſpecially ſeeing we learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lord &amp; Maſter Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>that the way is narrow that leadeth vnto eternall life, and that they are but few that finde it.</hi> Yet this difficultie of finding the way to heaven riſeth from the paſſengers wilfulneſſe, or want of care: for the truth is, that of the ſmall company that make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity in the world, the greateſt part (howſoever they diſguiſe themſelues in acting their parts on earth with a maske of religion) yet never aiming ſincerely at ſalvation for their end, wholly neglect the meanes, and ſo runne the broad way to hell. Others better weighing the ſhortneſſe and inſtability of this preſent life, and well foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their future mortality, in a ſtate moſt bleſſed, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15667:3"/>no leſſe accurſed, deſire earneſtly the joyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet never attending diligently to attaine them by that way, which God hath directed for that end; but relying vpon guides, whom they chooſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues at adventure to conduct them, are carried blindfold at the laſt thorough vncertaine by-paths to their certain ruine. It is true that God hath never failed in every age to ſend faithfull guides into the world, to direct his ſervants in this earthly paſſage; but it is likewiſe found true by woefull experience, that the Divell hath heere his ſwarmes of agents likewiſe to miſlead vs, and of thoſe, very many who haue learned the skill of their maſter, the Prince of darkneſſe, to transforme themſelues into the ſhape of the meſſengers of light. If wee looke to the Church, conſiſting of the Iewes alone before the comming of Chriſt, we finde it recorded by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets of God, that it was in continuall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by reaſon of falſe prophets, and ſeducing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, that did infeſt it; who<note n="a" place="margin">ler. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>propheſied in the name of God, when he ſent them not;</hi> ſo that as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> complaineth,<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>The leaders of this people cauſed them to erre, and they that were led by them, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi> When Chriſt our Saviour came into the world, who were they that moſt oppoſed him, but the Scribes, the Phariſies, the high Prieſts, who were then eſteemed, and tooke vpon them to be the guides and leaders of the people: nay to diſcourage their Nation from receiving the doctrine of their ſalvation, they thought it enough to preſſe this,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15667:4"/>queſtion;<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 7.48.</note> 
               <hi>Doe any of the Rulers, or of the Phariſies beleeue in him? but this people that know not the Law,</hi> &amp;c. In the time of the Goſpell wee are forewarned of falſe teachers, that ſhall riſe vp in the Church, who ſhal come nevertheleſſe in the name of Chriſt, taking vpon them to be our guides; nay ſome of them ſhall put on ſo faire a vizard of outward carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as that they ſhall ſeduce (if it were poſſible) Gods choſen children. So that it will concerne vs no leſſe then the loſſe, or ſalvation of our ſoules, to be wary in our choice of the guides we follow, for though it be certaine, that the blinde, and ſeducing teacher, ſhall for his hire haue his portion in hell with his Maſter, for whom he laboured; yet muſt the ſeduced likewiſe know, that they cannot eſcape the judgement of God; &amp; ſo the one with the other fal at laſt into the pit of eternal ruine. But herein to make vs the more inexcuſable, almighty God, out of his infinit care of mans ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath not only fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned vs of theſe noyſome weeds, that ſhall daily ſpring vp in his Church, to the endangering of the corne; but to make vs able to diſcerne betweene the true Paſtors of his flocke, and thoſe impoſtors that endeavour to delude vs, he ſends vs none to treate with vs in this great affaire concerning our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but with inſtructions in writing, and thoſe open to our view; requiring vs, to whom theſe meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are ſent, to haue an eye to their commiſſion,<note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>To the Law and to the Testimony; if they ſpeake not according to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15667:4"/>them.</hi> It is true, that from the firſt creation of the world, for divers ages there was no written Word, but as God himſelfe was pleaſed to bee the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate teacher of our firſt parents, ſo afterwards fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time he raiſed vp preachers for his people, whom in divers manners hee inſpired with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and enabled for this worke of inſtructing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his true feare and ſervice. But when once it pleaſed God in his wiſdome to appoint <hi>Moſes,</hi> that holy man, to be the faithfull pen-man of his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Law, which he gaue for the government and direction of his Church: it is required as a duty of the people of God,<note n="e" place="margin">Ioſh. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>That this booke of the Law depart not out of their mouthes: That they meditate therein day and night, To obſerve and doe according to all that is written therein.</hi> And to reſtraine vs from wandring out of the compaſſe of this written law, this charge is giuen,<note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>That wee put nothing to the Word which hee commands vs, nor take ought therefrom, that wee may keepe the Commandements of the Lord our God, which are commanded.</hi> And although the Propheſies were penned after at ſundrie times by men vndoubtedly directed by the holy Ghoſt, yet ſhal we find no new article of doctrine delivered in them: but they ſerue many times to explaine the law. They Propheſie of Chriſt to come, the accompliſher of the law; and generally they are all Gods Heraulds to denounce his iudgements, and heavie wrath, againſt the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But in the fulneſſe of time, when Chriſt came into the world, of whome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15667:5"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets wrote, the Goſpell was publiſhed, which was no other but a cleare declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the propheſies, and the law; whereof a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father aptly giues this note,<note n="g" place="margin">Auguſt. de Carichiſand: Rud.</note> 
               <hi>That in the olde teſtament the New is hidden, and in the new is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation of the olde.</hi> And this Goſpel was firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but after (as one other of the Ancients obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth well)<note n="h" place="margin">Iren. adverſ. haereſ. l. 3. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>was by the will of God delivered in the Scriptures, to be the pillar and foundation of our faith.</hi> And in this ſacred booke is wonderfully ſet foorth vnto vs the infinite wiſdome of the ſupreame Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker of the world: for as in the civill government of earthly Kingdomes, thoſe lawes are ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended moſt, that leave leaſt to the diſcretion of the Iudge, and never hath any common-weale had laws ſo exactly framed, but with time they haue bin ſound ſenſibly defectiue in this point; ſo certainely this perfection is peculiar only to the written laws of the Lord of heaven, ſo farre foorth, that for the miniſters of this law to adde or alter any one thing, reſpecting the religious dutie and ſervice wee owe to God (though but in offering ſtrange fire before the Lord, as did <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>) makes them liable to his wrath and maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for their preſumption. This moued Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> that reverend Father (alluding to the words of the bleſſed Apoſtle) confidently to pronounce,<note n="i" place="margin">Contra Lit. Petilian. lib. 3. cap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>That whether concerning Chriſt, or concerning the Church of Christ, or concerning any thing that pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to our faith and life, we will not ſay, if we, but if an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15667:5"/>Angell from heaven ſhall preach vnto you, but what you haue received in the Scriptures of the Law and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, accurſed be hee.</hi> The conſideration of this gaue me occaſion to forſake my communion with the Church of Rome, in whoſe boſome I receiued the firſt inſtruction for matter of my ſalvation, as you your ſelfe (deare Mother) can well remember. But after divers yeares, when by accident this principle had taken impreſſion in me,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>That faith commeth by hearing of the word of God,</hi> and then calling to mind, that many points of the religion I haue embraced, were not to bee found within the volume of Gods ſacred booke; I began to queſtion with my maſters of that Church (whom I did then reverence and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire as men wholly compoſed to devotion and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie) by what authority they could approve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; where after many paffages (with the relation wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I thinke not fit to trouble you) their reſolution was, <hi>That a great portion of Gods word was not</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Little of Gods word is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to writing, the greateſt part of it is come to vs by tradition. <hi>Hoſius Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ: Polon: pag 383.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within the holy Scriptures, but delivered in ſafe cuſtodie, to paſſe from hand to hand by tradition:</hi> for the truth and certainty whereof, they tolde me, I muſt depend vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>the credit of their</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Alphonſ: 2 Caſtro adverſ. haereſ. l. 1. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Church;</hi> the which, after much debate, they reſolved at the laſt into the boſome of the<note n="n" place="margin">Mater Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia per os<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſummi ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis loquens. Bellar. Apol. contra praef: monito: ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſi Reg. Iac. pag. 78.</note> 
               <hi>Romane Biſhop:</hi> when I conſidered this, and perceiued in the end the weakneſſe of the grounds that muſt warrant the truth of theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities (as they ſtyle them) I thought it no longer ſafe-to commit my ſelfe for direction to thoſe guides, my maſiers, I meane, of the Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15667:6"/>of Rome, of whom in my conſcience we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> did of the falſe teachers in his dayes,<note n="o" place="margin">Ierem. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>They haue reiected the word of the Lord, and what wiſedome is then in them.</hi> For although it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denied, but they reteine and publiſh ſome principles of our Chriſtian profeſſion, according to the truth of Gods holy word; yet even thoſe truths they recommend vnto vs, vpon as perillous &amp; falſe a ground, as if a man ſhould therfore beleeue Chriſt Jeſus to be the Sonne of the living God, becauſe the Divell did confeſſe it. To this purpoſe (deare Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) I beſeech you to note, that whereas Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word is left vnto vs to be the rule and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our faith and religion, my maſters of Rome intending to build a new, thinke it proper firſt to lay a new foundation, &amp; in place of the holy Scriptures to be the rule &amp; direction of our faith, they adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their Church, the which nevertheleſſe being rightly vnderſtood, holds no reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the Church in truth. And the rather to invite vs to pin our faith vpon this their Church, they tender vs ſome formes of truth, the which when wee haue embraced vpon their Churches authority, ſhee will not leaue vs ſo; but this Church that teacheth vs to worſhip God, by like authority wil then require vs <hi>to worſhip</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Seeing Chriſt is to be adored with divine worſhip, his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage alſo is to be adored with the ſame adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Tho: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin: part: 3. q. 25. art: 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</hi> Shee that teacheth vs to pray to God, wil command vs likewiſe to pray <hi>trourbleſſed Ladie, and the</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">The new Creed publiſhed by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth.</note> 
               <hi>Saints.</hi> Shee that teacheth vs, that Chriſt by one offring of his body, once made in ſacrifice vpon the Croſſe, hath purchaſed remiſſion for our ſinnes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15667:6"/>requireth vs likewiſe to beleene that ſhe offers day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto God the ſame reall body of Chriſt in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (which himſelfe offered vpon the Croſſe) as <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">I conſeſſe that in the Maſſe is offered to God a true, proper and propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the quicke and the dead: <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>propitiation for the ſinnes of the quicke and the dead.</hi> She that teacheth vs that Chriſt hath madeſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for his ſin by blood-ſhedding and bitter paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will teach vs withall, that our ſelues muſt make ſatisfaction for ſome ſort of our ſins, by our workes of penance; the which if wee neglect, that then wee muſt ſatisfie Gods juſtice for them after this life by ſuffering paines in a purgatory fire, vnleſſe this holy Mother out of compaſſion ſhall free vs by her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, <hi>á favour</hi> ſhe ſometimes affords <hi>to her zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous children,</hi> if my maſters <hi>of</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rhem: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: in Lue: cap. 23. v. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Rhemes</hi> bee not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Shee that teacheth vs to doe good workes, wil make vs beleeue they are<note n="t" place="margin">The heaven'y bleſſednes, which the Scripture calleth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the iuſt, is not give them of God <hi>gratis,</hi> and freely, but is due to their workes: yet God hath ſet forth heaven to ſale for our workes. <hi>Andraed: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox: expl:<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 6.</hi>
               </note> meritorious <hi>ex condigno,</hi> and ſo turne our Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duties into glorious ſins. Shee that teacheth vs that Gods written Word is true, will haue vs beleeue withall, <hi>That it containes</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Can: loc. l. 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>not all the doctrine of our ſalvation,</hi> and commaunds vs <hi>not to</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Index libit proh: <hi>Pij</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Reg. 4.</note> 
               <hi>reade it without her leaue, nor vnderſtande it but according to the ſence</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">No man may giue other expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Scriptures, there ſuch as might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the doctrine of the Church of Rome. <hi>Concil: Trid: Seſſ: 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhe giues vs.</hi> So that (if we marke it well) ſhee doth no more then the enemy of mankind is obſerved to doe, who many times for a vantage vtters truth, that after he may finde the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer paſſage to delude with error. And if the groſſe abſurdities, now currant in the Roman Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from theſe formes of truth, were laide open to the view of all men, I am perſwaded in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there is not ſo ſimple a Chriſtian living at this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15667:7"/>day, that makes any care of his dutie to God, but would abhorre them. But herein my maſters of Rome declare themſelues ingenious in their craft, who wel foreſeeing that this coine cannot paſſe for currant in the light, vent it ever in the darke; ſo that of many thouſands that receiue it, ſcarſe any one doth vnderſtand it in particular; and if any Lay-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, more curious then others, come by chance to know it, yet admitting the principles which he muſt learne withal, it is no more poſſible for him to judge of it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any man in the darke to diſcerne of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors: for as the eye of the body is not vſeful at al, but in the light, no more is our vnderſtanding enabled to diſtinguiſh betweene truth and errour in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of chriſtianity, but in the glorious light of the holy Scriptures. The ignorance of theſe is aſſigned by Chriſt our Saviour<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 22.29.</note> to be a reaſon of error, and we are taught by the Prophet <hi>David, That the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal: 119. verſ. 130.</note> 
               <hi>ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods word giueth light, that it giueth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the ſimple.</hi> With him the bleſſed Apoſtle accords,<note n="b" place="margin">Tim. 3.15.</note> and tels vs, that <hi>the holy Scriptures are able to make vs wiſe vnto ſalvation.</hi> This wiſedome my maſters of Rome approue not in the Laytie: they like beſt that ſcholler, that ſooneſt learnes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelfe with the<note n="c" place="margin">Recorded and commended by <hi>Staphylus, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> and others.</note> 
               <hi>Colliars Creede,</hi> To beleeue in groſſe, as doth their Church, without being able to render a reaſon of any article of the religion hee profeſſeth. It is gravely delivered by the Rhemiſts in their annotations vpon Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpell,<note n="d" place="margin">Rhem: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: on Luk: 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>That if a Catholike man being called before the commiſsion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15667:7"/>anſwere, that he is a Catholike man, and that he will liue and die in that faith, which the Catholike Church teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and that this Church can giue them a reaſon of al the things which they demand of him, hee anſweres enough, and defends himſelfe ſufficiently.</hi> Now the better to prepare the Laytie to this ſufficiencie, they permit them not to reade the Scriptures, but with licence, and never but with this caution, to admit no other ſence of what they reade in them, but ſuch, as theſe my maſters vnder the name of the Catholike Church ſhall recommend vnto them: By which wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſleight, they deprive them of al vſe of their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the matter of their ſalvation, and of the Scriptures, both at once; and in place thereof leave them furniſhed only to maintain the doctrine they haue embraced, with the pretended name and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Catholike Church. For inſtance in this, giue me leave (deare Mother) without your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to appeale to your ſelfe; if it were demanded of you, by what warrant you hold it lawfull to pray to Saints, to worſhip Images, to pray for foules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and the like; your anſwere I preſume would be, that herein you follow the doctrine of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, which being ever directed by the holy Ghoſt cannot deceive vs. I muſt confeſſe, the authority of the Catholike Church rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ought much to moue vs, conſiſting in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſence of all that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany which in all ages, &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the world, haue joyned in profeſſion of al the principles of the true religion. But if to chalenge to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15667:8"/>our ſelues the name of the Church were of it ſelfe enough, without queſtion it would follow, that God ſhould haue as many Churches, as there haue bin hereſies in the world. For never haue there been any authors of thoſe impieties, but haue endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to giue them countenance vnder the ſhadow &amp; name of the Catholike Church. I wil not enter here into any diſcuſſion of the doctrine mainetained at this day in the Roman Church, which were, but to weede in a field of tares: the abſurdity of it is made viſible to the world, by the learned labours of many reverent and worthy Paſtors of our Church: I will only in this place declare, in what ſence my maſters of Rome vnderſtand the Catholike Church, with the ſound whereof they continually fill your eares, as being the maine ſupporters of al they teach you: And firſt this principle is worthy to be noted well, which we learne from the moſt eminent writer of the Papacie at this day,<note n="e" place="margin">Bellarm: de effect: ſacram: lab. 2. cap. 25.</note> 
               <hi>That the truth of all ancient Councels, and of all points of faith, dependeth vpon the authoritie of the preſent Church;</hi> where, if we deſire to know, what he meanes by the Church, the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals interpreter plainely tels vs,<note n="f" place="margin">Gretſer. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. Bellarm: com. 1. pag. 1450. B.</note> 
               <hi>That when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Church to be iudge of al controverſies of faith, by the Church they vnderstand the Biſhop of Rome, who for the time governes the ſhippe of the militant Church, and by liuely voice doth clearely and expreſſely expound his iudgement to them that ſeeke to him.</hi> To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, another great Rabbin amongſt them delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth plainely,<note n="g" place="margin">Gregor: de Valent. in Tho. 22. tom. 3. Diſput. 1. punct. 7. q 5.</note> 
               <hi>That the Apoſtolike Church is therefore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15667:8"/>faid to be infallible, becauſe he is over it, who by himſelfe hath infallible authority.</hi> And if wee would knowe who that <hi>He</hi> is, that hath this infallible authoritie, we may learne from the Jeſuite <hi>Swares,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Suares in 3. Thom. tom. 1. diſput. 44. ſect. 1. pag. 677.</note> 
               <hi>That it is the Pope whoſe determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he affirmes to be the truth, and were it contrary to the ſaying of all the Saints, yet to be preferred before them, nay if an Angell of heaven were oppoſed againſt him, yet the Popes determination were to be preferred.</hi> This man <hi>(the Pope)</hi> they ſtyle the viſible head of the Church, and affirme to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſo infallibly directed by the Spirit of God, as that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoever either of himſelfe alone, with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to enforme the Church, or affiſted with an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the learned, hee ſhall reſolue any queſtion concerning faith, or the ſervice of God, it is<note n="i" place="margin">The Pope is the maſter of our faith, and cannot but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the truth of faith, nor can be deceived or erre, if as chiefe Biſhop or maſter of our faith, he ſet downe his determination. <hi>Zumel: diſput: Var: tom. 3. pag. 49.</hi>
               </note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould bee deceived. If you aske of anie one of my maſters of Rome, what he meanes by the Church, which he propoſeth to you to bee the rule of your faith, hee will mannerly define it at the firſt to conſiſt of the Pope with a Councell; but if you ſhall further vrge him to confeſſe, what you muſt doe in caſe the Pope ſhal diſſent in iudgement from the Councell, howſoever he faulter in his ſpeech a while, he muſt acknowledge at the laſt,<note n="k" place="margin">Capiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de autor. Papae. p. 105.</note> 
               <hi>That if the Councell, and the Pope, publiſh constitutions that be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, that of the Popes muſt bee preferred, as being of greater authoritie.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Alvar. Pelag. de Planc: Eccl. lib. 1. Artic. 6.</note> 
               <hi>To whoſe iudgement alone</hi> (if wee may beleeue another of that crew) <hi>wee are rather bound to stand, then to the iudgement of all the worlde beſides: who himſelfe</hi> (as<note n="m" place="margin">De Chriſto. lib. 2. cap. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> mainetaines)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15667:9"/>
               <hi>without any Councell may decree matter of faith.</hi> So that by this (deare Mother) if you weigh it wel, you may plainely ſee, that howſoever my maſters of Rome dazell your eyes with the Churches name, the Pope alone beareth away the game, in ſuch ſort, that the faireſt certainety you can haue to ſecure your conſcience in the religion you profeſſe, muſt wholly depend vpon him: yet is it worthy of your ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervation to note, how the learned amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſcant vpon this viſible head, and infallible director of their Church. They will acknowledge, that the Pope may be as wicked a man in life, as any other in the world, and by experience it hath bin found, that ſundry of them haueſcarſe had matches in this kind, as for inſtance of one, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, whom <hi>Guicciardine</hi> (though himſelfe a Papiſt) doth thus decypher. <q>His manners and cuſtomes were diſhoneſt, little ſinceritie in his adminiſtrations, no ſhame in his face, ſmall truth in his words, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith in his heart, &amp; leſſe religion in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: all his actions were defaced with vnſatiable covetouſneſſe, immoderate ambition, barbarous crueltie: he was not aſhamed, contrary to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of former Popes (who to caſt ſome colour over their infamie, were wont to call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes) to call his ſonnes his children; and for ſuch to expreſſe them to the world:<note n="n" place="margin">Guicciards lib. 3.</note> The bruite went, that in the loue of his daughter <hi>Lucretia,</hi> were concurrent not only his two ſons, the Duke of Candy, and the Cardinall of Valence, but him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15667:9"/>ſelfe alſo, that was her father: who as ſoone as he was choſen Pope, tooke her from her husband, and married her to the Lord of Peſare, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuffer her husband to be his corrival, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved that mariage alſo, and tooke her to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by vertue of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> keyes<note n="o" place="margin">Lib. 6.</note>: It was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other graces his naturall cuſtome to vſe poyſonings, not onely to be revenged of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but alſo to diſpoile the wealthy Cardinals of their riches: And this he ſpared not to doe againſt his deareſt friend, till at the laſt, having a purpoſe at a banquet to poiſon divers Cardinals, and for that end appointed his Cup-bearer to giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance with wine made ready for the nonce (who miſtaking the bottle, gaue the poiſoned cup to him) was thus himſelfe diſpatched by the juſt judgement of God, that purpoſed to murder his friends; that he might be their heire</q> Thus far the hiſtorian: Now as in life, ſo is it not denied by my maſters of Rome, but that the Pope may erre in his private opinions; Nay <hi>Boſius</hi> (though moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the Sea of Rome) confeſſeth,<note n="p" place="margin">Tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de ſignis eccleſ: lib. 28. cap. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>That hee may be an Heretike,</hi> as was Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> whoſe hereſie is condemned of record by<note n="q" place="margin">Sinod. 6. act. 4.12.14. Sinod. 7. act. vlt. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. 8. act. 7.</note> three lawfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. Pope Iohn the 23. was condemned in the Councell of Conſtance, for maintaining the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his maſter <hi>Epieurus,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Concil: Conſtant. Seſ. 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>That there was no eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, no immortality of the ſoule, nor reſurrection from the dead.</hi> Yet if Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth at leaſure from his lewdnes, or Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15667:10"/>ſhal from their privat follies transforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into publike teachers, and pronounce a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in any queſtion, that may be moued of any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Chriſtian religion, purpoſely to direct the Church; In this caſe, by the doctrine of my maſters of Rome, you ſhall bee bound to beleeue them no leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if God himſelfe had taught you. To which purpoſe, <hi>Stapleton</hi> the Prieſt hath left this for a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Stapleton, praef. princip. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. doctrin.</note> 
               <hi>That the foundation of our religion is of neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie placed vpon this mans teaching, in which we heare God himſelfe ſpeaking.</hi> To this fallacie, vnder the Churclies name, they adde another, whereby they endevour to delude you, framed vpon a falſe poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely this, That all our forefathers haue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the ſame religion in every point, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues profeſſe and teach you: from whence they prepare a queſtion, the which they recommend to their ſchollers to oppoſe <hi>adomnia:</hi> Shall we thinke our ſelues wiſer then all our forefathers? If a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of <hi>Mahomets</hi> impieties (which haue bewitched a great portion of the world, for many hundreds of yeares now paſt) being perſwaded by my maſters of Rome to become a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould queſtion thus, ſhal I thinke myſelfe wiſer then my forefathers, for theſe thouſand yeares now paſt, haue bin? I know their judgement would ſerve them to reply, that he muſt not follow his forefathers, vnleſſe they had beene followers of the truth of God: My maſters of Rome will tell you, that this holds no reſemblance with them, who dare giue you their words for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15667:10"/>that every article of their doctrine is derived from our Saviour Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe their art of begging is but a vagrant faſhion, but if it ſhal pleaſe you to ſee ſome trial of the truth of this, I dare preſume it ſhall be made evidently to appeare vnto you in the preſence of any that would oppoſe it that their principle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Popes ſpirit of infallibility (being the maine ſupporter of all religion at this day in the Church of Rome) is not ſo ancient by many ages in the world, as is the Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran of that accurſed <hi>Mahomet.</hi> If the foundation be proved new, what rule can they propoſe to ſecure your conſcience for the antiquity of the building: their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued Prieſthood, their daily ſacrifice, their ſatisfactions for ſinne, their workes of merit, their reall change in the Sacrament, their adoration of it, their mangled communion, their worſhip of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their prayers to Saints, their Auricular Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, their Purgatory fire, with all that trumperie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, which they tender vnder the name, and diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed habite of Church traditions? Certainly all theſe are <hi>terrae filij:</hi> If they ſeeke to the Scriptures for their originall, they will be ſent packing with <hi>we know you not:</hi> Poſſibly it may be demanded, what I thinke of our forefathers, who liued in the latter ages of the world, while theſe miſts of Popery lay thicke vpon the face of the viſible Church, in theſe Weſterne parts: Were they damned all? God forbid, that any man ſhould be ſo ſavage to write or think ſo: I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeve, and haue beene alwaies taught ſo, that as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15667:11"/>well the Church of England, as other of forraine parts, when the tyranny and corruptions of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie did moſt oppreſſe them, were nevertheleſſe portions of Gods vniverſall Church, and ſent many ſoules to God. For even in theſe, when they were moſt obſcured with errour and ignorance, yet all eſſentiall points of Chriſtian doctrine were to bee learned, touching the invocation and worſhippe of God, touching our redemption by Chriſt Ieſus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, touching our obſervation of Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, &amp; ſo the reſt: ſo that concerning out fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers this may ſuffice, that as wee are bound in Chriſtian charitie, to hope the beſt of their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that before vs embraced the faith of Chriſt (though poſſibly divers of them might approue in groſſe ſome errors of the time wherein they liued, never apprehending in particular the ſcope &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them) ſo yet is it no way ſafe for vs to make our forefathers our rule of faith. In the Church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the Iewes before Chriſts comming into the world, the holy Prophets of God were ſo farre from making their forefathers a rule to follow, as that to the contrary we ſhal finde nothing more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with them, then to warne the people of God, <hi>That they walke not in the ordinances of their fathers.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 78.8.</note> 
               <hi>Not to be as their forefathers, a faithleſſe &amp; ſtabborne generation: a generation that ſet not their heart aright,</hi> &amp;c. and to like purpoſe in ſundry places. But for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this point, it is our part to follow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that holy Martyr of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15667:11"/>Church:<note n="u" place="margin">Lib. 2. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 3.</note> 
               <hi>If Chriſt onely bee to bee heard, not to liſten what any man before vs hath thought fit to be done, but what Chriſt hath done, who is before all, for that wee are not to follow the cuſtome of men, but the truth of God.</hi> My maſters of Rome (if there be no remedy) will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this poſition of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> marry then you muſt giue them leaue to begge and aſſume this truth of God, to bee the proper inheritance of the Biſhop, and Church of Rome; but if you ſhall deale ſo vnfriendly with them, as to preſſe them to ſhew their evidence, they wil trouble you with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but in the end, for your ſatisfaction, this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere muſt content you, or none at all, <hi>dixit Eccleſia,</hi> themſelues will tell you ſo. The Paſtors of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of England, will likewiſe make claime of this truth of God, to reſt with them; but herein they wil deale more ingeniouſly with you, then the other, they will deſire you to beleeue them no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this point, then by plaine demonſtration out of Gods holy word they ſhall be able to make good their claime. In this confuſion and difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene our teachers (pretending of either ſide to haue the Church and truth of God; and yet impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that in ſo direct a contrarietie as reſteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, of one ſide they muſt needs abuſe vs) poſſibly (deare Mother) you will aske, what meanes are left for vs, that are but learners in the ſchoole of Chriſt, to diſcerne betweene them? To cenſure their doctrine by their liues and actions, were an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine way, a reaſon whereof wee learne from Saint
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15667:12"/>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> an ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Father of the Church:<note n="x" place="margin">Homil. 49. in Matt. oper. imperf.</note> 
               <q>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whatſoever kinde of holines the ſervants of God haue in truth, the ſervants of Satan may have in likenes: for the divell hath his that be meeke and humble, that be chaſt, and giue almes, that faſt, and doe every good deed, which God hath appointed for the ſalvation of mankinde; and theſe formes of godlines hath the Divell brought in, to ſeduce vs; that a confuſion being made betweene good and counterfeit; ſimple men, which know not the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene goodnes indeed, and goodnes in ſhew, while they ſeeke the good ſervants of God, might light vpon the Divels ſeducements.</q> Of this mind are likewiſe the learned of the Church of Rome,<note n="y" place="margin">Part. 6. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> 
               <hi>You know</hi> (ſaith Maſter <hi>Harding</hi> in his confutation of Biſhop <hi>Iewels</hi> Apologie) <hi>it is no good argument to reaſon from manners to the doctrine: who would not hiſſe and trample you out of the ſchooles, if you make this argument: The Papists liues be faultie,</hi> Ergo, <hi>their teaching is falſe.</hi> I know that howſoever my maſter of Rome like not (as you ſee) to haue their doctrine meaſured by the line of their liues and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet themſelues will offer crooked meaſure in this kind: there is nothing more familiar with them in their publike writings, or private diſcourſe with their ſchollers, that admire them, then to traduce and vilifie the Paſtors of the Church of England, of whom certainly many there haue beene, and are of excellent merit and example in the Church, and no doubt but ſome in ſo great a number may be found
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15667:12"/>ſcandalous in their places, who can expect no other, but a feareful judgement in the end. But if this were an argument, wee need not ſeeke for proofe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny adverſe to the Church of Rome, but from their own records; as for inſtance in one, I pray you (deare Mother) note, what <hi>Aventine</hi> a learned hiſtorian of their owne diſcloſeth:<note n="z" place="margin">Annal. lib. 6. in initio.</note> 
               <q>The Pope ſetteth over the flocke of Chriſt goates, wolues, luſtfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, adulterers, raviſhers of Virgins and Nunnes, cookes, muleters, thieues, bankers, vſurers, drones, game hunters, lecherous, perfidious, periured, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant aſſes: He committeth the ſheep to wolues and hypocrites, which only provide for their own bellies: Nay, hee ſetteth boyes and wantons to rule the lambes: I am aſhamed to ſay what manner of Biſhops we have: with the revenews of the poore they feede their hounds, horſes, whoores, they quaffe, they loue, the fly learning as infection, &amp;c.</q> thus farre the Hiſtorian. But my maſters of Rome will tell you, they haue an vndoubted way to aſſure you of the doctrine they teach you, to bee the truth of God; which is, by meanes of the miracles, they boaſt to be frequent with them: I wil confeſſe (if we may beleeve them) it hath been as eaſie and familiar with them to worke a wonder, as it hath been with the Pope to make a Saint, and yet I muſt tell you, ſome doctors of his owne<note n="a" place="margin">Canus, loc. l. 5. c. 5. q. 5. Concl. 3. Cajetan <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>make doubt, whether al be Saints in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the Popes have canonized for ſuch,</hi> and thruſt into the Romane Calender. But to the miracles, which they can chalenge as proper to their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15667:13"/>Church, ſince their Biſhops of that Sea haue aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the ſeate of their Vniverſall Soveraignetie, if they were all true (as for the moſt part queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they are but fables &amp; impoſtures, ſuch as thoſe of the Legend are obſerved to be, by men judicious, and learned among themſelves, as <hi>Canus,</hi> that plainly ſtiles the writer of them<note n="b" place="margin">Canus, loc. l. 11. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>a man of a braſen face, and a leaden heart; Eſpenceus</hi> that affirmes,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 4. digr. 25.</note> 
               <hi>No ſtable to be ſo ful of dongue, as the Legends are ful of lies</hi>) yet could this prove no certaine meane to aſſure vs of the truth to be with them, ſeeing (as <hi>Stapleton,</hi> one of their Prieſts confeſſeth)<note n="d" place="margin">Stapleton. prompt. mor: part: aſtiu: in Dominic 24. poſt Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt.</note> 
               <hi>For the more triall of the godly, not only Antichriſt himſelfe, and his forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but all heretikes alſo may doe true miracles, by the permiſsion of God; as the Sorcerers of Pharaoh did.</hi> And greater, I preſume, my maſters of <hi>Rome</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not boaſt of in theſe later times, then <hi>Baronius</hi> the Cardinall hath recorded to be done by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the divel,<note n="e" place="margin">Anno: 63. num. 22.</note> 
               <hi>That he made Images to walke, and would lye in the fire without hurt, that hee would flye in the ayre, and make bread of ſtones, that he could open doores fast ſhut, vnlooſe bonds of iron; that hee had many ſhadowes following him, as it had bin men,</hi> &amp;c. The like we may reade of others of that kinde. But for reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this point, I will here ſet downe a diſcourſe of a learned Father, the which is well worthy of your obſervation:<note n="f" place="margin">Chryſoſt: oper. imperf: num. 49.</note> 
               <q>Since Hereſies have gained place in the Church, there can bee no proofe of true Chriſtianitie, neither refuge for Chriſtians willing to know the truth, but the holy Scriptures:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15667:13"/>Hereto fore it was by many means declared which was the Church of Chriſt, and which was Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme; but now there is no way for thoſe that are willing to know which is the true Church of Chriſt, but by the Scriptures only: wherefore? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all thoſe things that properly belong to Chriſt in truth, Hereſies likewiſe haue in ſchiſme: they haue churches, they haue the holy ſcriptures they haue Biſhops &amp; other orders of the Clergie: they have Baptiſme, the holy Euchariſt, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, yea Chriſt himſelfe: whoſoever ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is willing to know which is the true Church of Chriſt, how ſhal he know it in the confuſion of ſo great reſemblance, but by the Scriptures only? Heretofore it was knowne by miracles, which were true Chriſtians, which falſe: by what means? The falſe, either could not work ſignes as the true Chriſtians did, or at leaſt not ſuch as true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s could: But now the working of miracles is wholly ceaſed, and it is obſerved, that counterfeit ſignes are more wrought with them that are falſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: Nay <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Clement</hi> hath foreſhewed, that Antichriſt ſhal haue power giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to work true miracles. Heretofore by the outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſation the Church of Chriſt might be knowne, when the lives of Chriſtians, either all or the moſt part were holy, ſuch as it was not with others: but now Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are become as bad, or worſe, then heretikes or Gentiles: nay there is a better outward carriage many times obſerved amongſt thoſe that are in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15667:14"/>Schiſme, then amongſt Chriſtians. Hee therefore that would know which is the true Church of Chriſt, how ſhould hee know it, but only by the Scriptures. Our Lord therefore knowing that ſo great confuſion of things would happen in the laſt dayes, commands Chriſtians, that deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue aſſurance of true faith, to fly to nothing but the holy Scriptures. If they looke to other things they ſhall be ſcandalized and periſh, not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which is the true Church, and thereby ſhall light vpon the abomination of deſolation, which ſhall ſtand in the holy places of the Church, &amp;c.</q> Thus far S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> My maſters of Rome (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they gloſe it) like not the language of this learned Father. To wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to expoſe their Church and doctrine, to bee judged by the holy Scriptures, <hi>were a hard ſaying,</hi> &amp; with the Capernaites<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 6.60.</note> in good reaſon they may tell you, <hi>they cannot beare it.</hi> But if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> had dealt ſo friendly with them, as in place of (onely Scriptures) to haue named the word of God, defining that word to conſiſt as well of vnwritten traditions, as the written word; &amp; had withall aſſigned the Church of Rome, with her ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Paſtor, to be the truſtie treaſurer of vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities, and the only infallible interpreter of the written word, whereof the Cardinals concluſion might haue beene made good,<note n="h" place="margin">Hoſius de expreſſ. Dei verbo. pag. 38.</note> 
               <hi>That which pleaſeth the Church is Gods expreſſe word;</hi> and at the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving this Church into the Pope<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the name of church, we vnderſtand her head, that is to ſay, the Rom. or biſhop. <hi>Greg. de valent. in Tho. tom. 3. diſput. 1. quaeſt. 1. punct. 1.</hi>
               </note> alone, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe they would haue taken it as a kindnes at his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15667:14"/>hands. But if he will inſiſt vpon <hi>only Scriptures</hi> they will never giue over cavelling at this point: Firſt they will tell him,<note n="k" place="margin">Canus loc. l. 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>that many things belong to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, which are contained in the Scriptures nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther openly, nor obſcurely:</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> it ſeemes was of another mind, who affirmeth,<note n="l" place="margin">In Mat. hom. 45.</note> 
               <hi>That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is required to ſalvation is all, accompliſhed in the Scriptures, neither is any thing wanting there, that is needfull for mans ſalvation:</hi> which mooues another of the antients to adviſe,<note n="m" place="margin">Iſidorus Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſiota lib. 1. ep. 369.</note> 
               <hi>That we refuſe whatſoeuer is taught, vnleſſe it bee contained in the volume of the Bible:</hi> a reaſon whereof, <hi>Cyril,</hi> a learned Father giues,<note n="n" place="margin">lib. 72. in Ioh. haec aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptaſunt, &amp;c</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ſuch things are written, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles ſaw ſuffïcient for our faith and manners.</hi> Poſſibly, if they be intreated much, in good nature they will acknowledge at the laſt, (as <hi>Biſhop</hi> the Seminarie doth in his Tract againſt M. <hi>Perkins</hi> of Traditions)<note n="o" place="margin">The ſcriptures containe not the reſolution of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties which the learned muſt beleeue, if they will be ſaved: <hi>Biſhop</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Perkins.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the doctrine of ſalvation (at least ſo much as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſimple Christian is bound to beleeue vnder perill of damnation) is contained in the holy Scriptures; though not ſo for himſelfe, and his learned brethren:</hi> but then will they taxe the Scriptures with obſcuritie, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you from medling with them, vnder that pretenſe affirming, that they cannot be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the capacitie of the vulgar &amp; vnlearned rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. To this I oppoſe the iudgement of S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who plainely tels vs<note n="p" place="margin">Enarrat. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. 8.</note> 
               <hi>That God hath howed downe the Scriptures, even to the capacitie of babes and ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; That when proud men will not ſpeake to their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, yet himſelfe might.</hi> To like purpoſe S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15667:15"/>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Homil. 3. de Lazaro.</note> 
               <hi>That God hath penned the Scriptures by the hands of Publicans, Fiſhermen, Tentmakers, Shepherds, Neatherds, and vnlearned men; that none of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people might haue any excuſe, to keep them from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and that ſo they might bee eaſily vnderſtood of all men, the Artificer, the Houſholder, and widows woman, and him that is most vnlearned, &amp;c.</hi> thus he. To the reſolution of theſe learned Fathers, my Maſters of Rome will reply with a queſtion; If the doctrine of ſalvation be ſo plainely propoſed in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; how it ſhould come to paſſe, that it is ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſely vnderſtood? <hi>Arrius</hi> reads it, &amp; denies the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie of Chriſt; <hi>Eutiches</hi> reads it, and denies his humanitie; the Graecians read it, and eſteeme it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; The Jewes read it, and are offended at it. It is read at this day in the Church of Rome, as likewiſe in the Church in the communion whereof wee liue, and different opinions are collected from it; yet of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, it is true, there are men of excellent gifts, both for wit, &amp; learning. As if my Maſters of <hi>Rome</hi> were ignorant, that wit and learning (if not guided by the holy Ghoſt) were ſo farre from being means to further vs to a right vnderſtanding of Gods word, as that the more they abound in any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from grace, the more irrecouerable many times they plunge him into errour &amp; deluſion: for as the light of the Sunne though viſible, yet is not diſcerned by a blinde man, even ſo, although it bee true (which S. <hi>Austin</hi> teacheth)<note n="r" place="margin">De doctr. Chriſt. lib. 2. cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>That thoſe things which concerne our faith, &amp; converſation, yea all things
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15667:15"/>neceſſarie, are plainely, and manifestly ſet downe, in the holy Scriptures;</hi> yet the doctrine of ſalvation contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them, being the obiect of faith, not of witte, and humane learning (which faith is the ſpeciall worke of the holy Ghoſt in man) and never rightly, and vſefully vnderſtood, &amp; beleeved of any, but ſuch only, as ſincerely applying themſelues to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes of ſeeking inſtruction, by hearing, and reading Gods holy word, obtaine withal by hearty prayer, the direction of Gods bleſſed ſpirit:<note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>for the naturall man perceiveth not the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are diſcerned ſpiritually</hi> (as the Apoſtle tels vs.) My maſters of Rome wil heere be carping with a queſtion, whether every reader or hearer of the ſcriptures, may aſſure himſelfe to haue the ſpirit of God? I ſay not ſo, <hi>ſpiritus vhi vult ſpirat:</hi> but this I ſay, and am aſſured that I ſay the truth,<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>that he that hath not the ſpirit of Christ, the ſame is none of his:</hi> and in an other place we are plainely taught,<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>That they that are governed by the ſpirit of God, they are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God:</hi> from al which this concluſion wil cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, that as it is impoſſible for vs (vnleſſe by hearing, or reading, we acquaint our ſelues with the language of the holy ſcriptures) to diſtinguiſh with the ſheep of Chriſt, between the ſhepheards voice, and the voice of ſtrangers; ſo it is our part, ſeriouſly, and from the heart, to ſeeke to God to enlighten our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding by the gift of his holy ſpirit; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, this everlaſting word of life proues to none, but the ſavour of death to their eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15667:16"/>My maſters of Rome I preſume will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to acknowledge this, that there is no true ſervant of God, but hath in this life the holy Ghoſt for <hi>a pledge of his adoption</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>which teſtifieth to his ſpirit that he is the child of God:</hi> and ſhame (I thinke) will not ſuffer them to make it queſtionable, whether this ſpirit of God, that was ſo powerfull with the bleſſed Apoſtles, as from vnlearned Fiſhermen (as diverſe of them were) to enable them for teachers of the world, may likewiſe bee now of power, to prepare the heart of the ſimpleſt hearer, or reader of Gods holy word, truely to apprehend therein the myſteries of his ſalvation. But how ſhall any man (ſay they) be certaine, that he hath the ſpirit of god? I muſt confeſſe, the truth of this is felt before it can be learned: yet as the man that hath his bodily ſight being demanded how hee can bee certaine that bee hath his eyes? could giue no other anſwer, but that by ſeeing he is aſſured that he hath his eyes; and by his eyes he is aſſured that he ſees; even ſo the ſpirit of God being the eye whereby the ſoule diſcerneth in ſpirituall things, the inward light of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Gods faithfull ſeruants, apprehending and beleeuing the grounds of faith deliuered in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, aſſures them, that they haue the ſpirit of God abiding in them, and by the ſame ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing vnto them out of Gods holy word (which is infallible the doctrine of ſalvation, their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are ſecured, that they vnderſtand and beleeue the truth. Yet would I not be thought to hold, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15667:16"/>every faithfull Chriſtian in this life, did attaine to a perfect knowledge of all the deepe myſteries that are to be found within the booke of God: I knowe there is depth for the Elephant to ſwimme, and ſafe place for the Lambe to wade in, and it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that (ſince the Apoſtles, &amp; Evangeliſts left the world) the holy Ghoſt (to hold the children of God in humility, &amp; to moue them the more carefully to attend the ſubordinate meanes preſcribed for the gaining of Chriſtian learning, as ferve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayer, with diligence in hearing Gods word preached &amp;taught by the paſtors of his Church, and ſeeking to them for their helpe and inſtruction vpon all occaſions of doubt, hath tempered their knowledge with ſuch meaſure, as that they ſhall but vnderſtand in part; yet ſhall they never faile to vnderſtand ſo much as ſhal ſuffice to bring them to a ſauing faith. But here a queſtion may be moued, ſeeing it is true (as in part I haue noted) that God by his ordinance hath aſſigned the miniſtery of the Church (I meane the inſtructions of her Paſtors, both private &amp; pub-like) to bee one meane, to bring his children to the knowledge of his truth, whether it be impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs that are of the Laitie, and learners in Gods Church, as a duty, to beleeue the doctrine our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors teach vs, without examination? My maſters of Rome, if you ſhall bee pleaſed to demaund of them, whether it may bee lawfull for you to examine the doctrine they recommend vnto you, their anſwere you may ſee in the annotations of the Rhemiſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15667:17"/>teſtament,<note n="y" place="margin">Rhem: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. act. 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>That you muſt not try, and iudge, whether your teachers doctrine be true or no, neither may you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that which you finde not in the ſcriptures.</hi> If you ſhal reply, and demaunde of them, to what purpoſe the holy Ghoſt then forwarned vs of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that ſhal come into the world; of ravenous Wolues, that ſhal invade the Church; of ſeducers, that ſhal ſo plauſibly carry themſelues, as that they ſhal deceiue (if poſſible) Gods choſen children: they wil ful wiſely tel you that al this hath no reſpect to them, who (vpon their words wee may beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if wee liſt) are the true paſtors of the Catholike church, which cannot erre; whereas (God wot) like petty chapmen they vent no other, but the deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wares of the great merchant, the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder the counterfeit marke &amp; name of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like church. But to the point in hand, it is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Chriſt in general to al his ſervants,<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>That they beware of falſe Prophets, to</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>try the ſpirits, not to beleeue every ſpirit.</hi> Al which of neceſſity muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe ſome examination, wherein we are not to follow our owne reaſon, fancie, or private ſpirit, but to be guided by that rule, which for this purpoſe the body Prophet doth direct,<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>the teſtimony and the law:</hi> from precept if we paſſe to example, wee ſhal finde it recorded to the perpetual praiſe of the men of <hi>Berea,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Sect. 17.11.</note> that when the Apoſtle preached Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them out of the law and the Prophets, <hi>they dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearched in the holy ſcriptures, whether thoſe things be delivered were ſo or no.</hi> And was it lawful &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15667:17"/>commendable in theſe good Chriſtians to examine the doctrine. which was taught the by that elected veſſel of God; and wil theſe <hi>Lucifugi</hi> of Rome make you beleeue its ſince for you to hold the like courſe with them: It may be my in afters of Rome for once wil beare with theſe men of <hi>Berea,</hi> and yet not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue their doing, as a rule to follow: Poſſibly they wil not ſtick to tel vs, that in the Churches infancie they were not ſo wel inſtructed in good manners, as ſince the ſcholler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Romame church haue bin: But ſhal wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſay they) ſhal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnlearned be fit &amp; able to iudge of their paſtors inſtruction? I would know of theſe my maſters, whether <hi>Lydia</hi> the purple ſeller, the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is written,<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>That God ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her heart,</hi> were then fit &amp; able to judge between the doctrine of the Pharifies refuſing Chriſt yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> &amp; the Apoſtles inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the bleſſed meſſenger of the Goſpell of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were <hi>Priſcilla</hi> with her husband <hi>Aquila,</hi> fit and able to judge of the doctrine of a worthy Paſtor of the Church,<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 18.26.</note> 
               <hi>Whom, after they had heard, they tooke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately vnto them, and instructed in the way of God more perfectly?</hi> Queſtionleſſe if any <hi>Priſcilla</hi> ſhould be ſo bould at this day with the meaneſt of my maſters of Rome, ſhe ſhould bee ſent packing with the ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full phraſe of <hi>Scripturist, Scripturian, doctoreſſe, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoleſſe,</hi> or ſome ſuch foolery: But Wiſdome is juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of her children: wee are taught by the, bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>That the Scriptures are able to make vs wiſe vnto ſalvation;</hi> &amp; the Kingly Prophet accords with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15667:18"/>this and telleth vs,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>That the teſtimony of God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and giueth wiſedome vnto little ones.</hi> This wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome my maſters of Rome haue found fatall to them, and therefore, although for feare of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they dare not in plaine tearmes entertaine the holy Scriptures, (when they are encountred with them) with ſuch a greeting, as <hi>Ahab</hi> that wicked King gaue the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. Kin. 21.20</note> 
               <hi>Haſt thou found vs, o our enemie?</hi> Yet is it worthy (deare Mother) of your obſertatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to note by what wily ſleights &amp; ſtraines of wit they haue practiſed to depriue the world of all vſe of them. Firſt, they like not to have them tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into the vulgar tongue of euery natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the vnlearned and common ſort might come to know them. To this purpoſe I pray you marke a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites language:<note n="i" place="margin">Azotius. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. tom. 1. l. 8. c. 26.</note> 
               <hi>It is demanded</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>whether the ſacred Scriptures may be tranſlated into the mother tongue of every nation, that every one may the better reade &amp; vnderſtand them? I anſwere that Lutherans &amp; Calviniſts are in that hereſie, that they affirme the ſacred Scripture ought to be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into the vulgar language of all nations, againſt whom the Councell of Trent hath made a ſolemne decree:</hi> and with this Ieſuite agrees our countriman <hi>Reynolds</hi> the Prieſt.<note n="k" place="margin">Calvino-tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmus. p. 825.</note> 
               <hi>It ſeemes to me</hi> (ſaith this Seminary) <hi>that this prophane revealing of the divine miſteries is odiouſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the will of God, and to the nature of the myſteries themſelues.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ibid. p. 831.</note> 
               <hi>The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and great miſchiefes, which by the tranſlation of the Scripture haue riſen againſt the Maieſtie of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holineſſe of the Scripture it ſelfe, againſt the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15667:18"/>tranquilitie of States, againſt the faith and good conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of men, ſhould haue force enough vtterly to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſse theſe tranſlations, yea albeit they were ſupported by divine or Apostolicall authoritie:</hi> Thus he, My ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Rhemes notwithſtanding this (wiſely taking into their conſiderations<note n="m" place="margin">In their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to their tranſlation of the new teſtament.</note> 
               <hi>the preſent time, ſtate and condition of our countrey, vnto which divers things are either neceſsarie or profitable, and medicinable now, that otherwiſe in the peace of the Church were neither much requiſite, nor perchance wholly toller able)</hi> haue ſent vs a tranſlation, ſuch as it is, yet durſt they not ſend it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad alone, but vnder ſafe cuſtodie of their peeviſh Comment, which like a theefe lyes lurking by, to ſteale from the Reader the true ſence of this holy word. Thus you may ſee, how vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and againſt their appetite, they haue beene brought to tranſlate the Scriptures into our vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar language: Their next ſleight to bee noted, is the practiſe and deviſe they vſe to reſtraine and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs (that are of the Laitie) from reading in them: For whereas we finde it to haue beene fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with Chriſt and his Apoſtles (while they were converſant on the earth) to direct their ſchollers with<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 5.36.</note> 
               <hi>ſearch the ſcriptures,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Luc. 10.26.</note> 
               <hi>how readeſt thou,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let Gods word dwell plentifully in you,</hi> &amp; to ſuch like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>Pereſius</hi> a Popiſh Biſhop declaimeth thus,<note n="q" place="margin">De tradit. p. 45.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall no bounds be ſet to popular, rude, and carnal men? ſhall old men before they haue put off the filth of their minds, and young men that yet ſpeake like children, bee admitted to read the Scriptures? I ſuppoſe verily (&amp; my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15667:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>opinion fayles me not) this ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnder the pretenſe of piety was invented by the divell:</hi> Another of the ſame plume, to feare vs from reading Gods holy word, tels a ſtory of certaine men, that were poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of a divel;<note n="r" place="margin">Thirrac: de demoniacis, c. 21. th. 157.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe being but husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmen, they were able to diſcourſe of the holy Scriptures.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Index lib. prohibi: Pij. 4. Reg. 4.</note> It is true that by the rule of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth, ſuch of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie may read the Scriptures <hi>as haue licence from their lawfull Ordinary ſo to doe.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>But if any Lay perſon ſhall preſume to looke into the holy Scriptures without ſuch licence, he must knowe his penaltie to bee no leſse then to be dented the pardon of his ſinnes:</hi> The late Pope Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 8. better belike conſidering, how well it went with their triple crowne, when they kept the Laity wholly from ſearching into the book of God (as in<note n="u" place="margin">Linwood in conſt. t. prov. l. 5. titulo de Magiſtris: § quin.</note> times paſt they indeavoured) carpeth at the rule of his predeceſſour, and reſolueth at the laſt,<note n="x" place="margin">The obſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s of Pope Clement the <hi>8.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of Pope P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that notwithſtanding this conſtitution of Pope Pius, Biſhops haue no power at all to grant any ſuch licence to the Laitie of reading Gods holy words.</hi> Nevertheleſſe betweene the enterfiering of theſe holy Fathers, it paſſes in priat by my Maſters of Rhemes,<note n="y" place="margin">In their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to their tranſla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note> 
               <hi>That ſuch of the Laitie may be readers in Gods word, as are permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Ordinaries vpon certificate from their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Prieſt or Confeſſour, that they be humble, ſober, and diſcreet perſons, &amp;c.</hi> But I beſeech you note the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of all. Firſt, this diſcreet Lay reader muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this for a principle,<note n="z" place="margin">Hoſius Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Polon. p. 385.</note> 
               <hi>That little of Gods word is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to writing, That the greateſt part of it is come to vs by tradition; the which we muſt receaue from ours
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15667:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Catholike Mother declaring her ſelfe by the mouth of our holy father, the Pope of Rome:</hi> The next rule this diſcreet Lay reader muſt learne to follow, is,<note n="a" place="margin">Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Seſſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>That no man muſt giue any other expoſition of Scripture, then ſuch as might agree with the doctrine of the Crurch of Rome;</hi> a reaſon whereof <hi>Andradius</hi> (that great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor of the faith of Trent) can giue vs, becauſe,<note n="b" place="margin">Defenſ. ſid. Trident. l. 2.</note> 
               <hi>All power to interpret the Scriptures, and reveale the hidden mysteries of our religion, is giuen from heaven to the Popes, and their Councells.</hi> Where, though the Councells be placed as a page to attend the Pope, yet the reſolution of all is this (as before I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) that if the Councell ſhall diſſent in iudgement from the Pope,<note n="c" place="margin">Sententia Papae praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda eſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliorum: Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recremata: ſum: de Eccle l. 3. c. 64. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The iudgement of the Pope is to be preferred before the iudgement of all others;</hi> ſaith the Cardinall <hi>Turrecremata.</hi> Of whom another writer of the Roman Church in plaine toarmes affirmeth,<note n="d" place="margin">Zumel diſp: var: tom: 3. pag. 49:</note> 
               <hi>That he is the maſter of our faith, and cannot but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the truth of faith, nor can be deceaued or erre, if as chiefe Biſhop, and maſter of the faith, he ſet downe his determination.</hi> From all which it is evident (if you marke it well) that although theſe<note n="e" place="margin">Paulo 5. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeo. &amp;c. <hi>a dedication to the prefet Pope.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vicedet</hi> of Rome could never compaſſe wholly to ſuppreſſe the ſacred Scriptures (as with good diſcretion poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they might haue bin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, conſidering how eagerly this holy word purſues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill with hue &amp; cry; which was well obſerued by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. when in his familiar diſcourſe with his friend the <hi>Cardinall Bembus,</hi> he vttered this vnſavory ſpeech;<note n="f" place="margin">Quantum lucri apporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit nobis &amp; Curiae noſtrae fabula iſta de Ieſu Chriſto: Baleus de act. Rom. pontif. in Leone. l. 7.</note> 
               <hi>what profit hath this fable of Ieſus Chriſt brought to vs or our court</hi>) yet by vnſpeakeable ſleights and art
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15667:20"/>accompanied in theſe later ages of the world, with ſtrange ſucceſſe by Gods permiſſion, they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured, to bring the ſence of the holy ſcriptures in ſafe cuſtody to themſelues alone; &amp; then locking it faſt with a rabble of groſſe inventions (ſtyled the Churches traditions) in the cloſet of their breaſts, of both together they haue ingeniouſly framed the ladder wherby they haue mounted into the throne of their vſurped ſoveraignety, in ſpiritual, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dominion; &amp; then taking vpon themſelues alone to be the only never-erring oracles of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their children haue come to craue bread of them, in place of that they haue given the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtones; wherewithal nevertheleſſe <hi>for</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Although the Pope being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent of his own and others ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, drawe with him innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſoules to hell, there to bee tormented for ever; yet may no mortall man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue him for it, for that he is to iudge all men, &amp; himſelfe to bee iudged of no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>diſt. 40. ſi Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>manners ſake</hi> their hungry ſoules muſt reſt contented, although in the meane time they pine to death for want of the true food of life. Poſſibly you wil thinke I write in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, and miſreport them: O that I might be ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, as that you would giue me leaue, to avow the truth of theſe things before you, in the preſence of any one of my maſters of Rome, that would oppoſe it: They wil tel you, they may not be ſeene without peril of their liues, as the caſe ſtands with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this day in England; and it is true, that the lawes ſound out ſeverity againſt them, but in execution they finde them remiſſe enough: for my part I know, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my firſt acquaintance with them, they can equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in apparel, as wel as language; and ſeeme to bee any thing, ſaving what they are; &amp; for this purpoſe, I would ſurrender my iudgement to mine eies, and take them for ſuch, as their habit ſhould declare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15667:20"/>God is witnes with me I mallice not their perſons, I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe I cannot but condemne their craft, and pitty ſuch as are inchaunted by them. The truth is they are cruel Iaylors, and mure vp your vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in theſe things, as their cloſe priſoner; wel knowing, that if once they giue you but libertie to heare freely what might be ſaid againſt them, they are ſure to looſe you. I beſeech you (deare Mother) for the loue you beare to God, to thinke maturelie of this great affaire. It concernes your ſoule, &amp; that for eternitie; and your day of preparation, by the courſe of nature, is far declining. Certainly the fault of my maſters of <hi>Rome</hi> (who miſlead you) is inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, yet wil not their fault proue your excuſe: The account for your ſoule wil be required at your own hands: ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (without queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) will prove no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere at the judgement day: It is not only a feareful ſin, when it miſleads vs from the way of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a grievous puniſhment that purſues man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind for the firſt tranſgreſſion. I know your zeale to the ſervice of God is great, but zeale without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge carries with it in the holy Scriptures a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe: I cannot expect you ſhould vpon my ſaying aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue ſo long embraced, this only ſhall be my humble requeſt, &amp; that for his loue that ſuffered a bitter &amp; ignominious death, to bring vs to a life of glory and eternity, that you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſpeedily, to lend an indifferent eare to ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of this point, by perſons learned of either ſide, for which purpoſe (although the meanenes of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition may chalenge nothing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſtate of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15667:21"/>yet would I hope to finde the favour, for ſo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable a worke, as the good of a ſoule, which a kingdome cannot redeeme, that ſome learned Prieſt of the Romiſh faſhion, without perill of the lawe might be ſuffered to haue acceſſe to you; ſo that you would be willing to admit with all the preſence of ſome moderate, graue, and learned man of the contrary part, betweene whom, if it might pleaſe you to ſtand but attentiue with a mind free of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, my hope would be, and my vnfained prayer ſhould concurre with it, that God would bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to open your heart, as he did of <hi>Lydia</hi> that good woman, and make you able to diſcerne betweene his truth delivered in his holy word, and the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of the preſent Church of Rome. If you ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult herein with any one of my maſters of Rome, I know he would diſſwade you from this courſe; he would ſing Syrene-like, pretending this care, that it is not now ſafe for you to diſquiet your conſcience with queſtions of this kind; wheras in truth his aime only would be, to hold you ſtil a captiue in the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of error, ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſecurity. But God (I truſt) in his good time wil diſappoint their drifts, to whom fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my heart I will daily pray (as charity, conſcience and duty binds me) that in mercy he wil be pleaſed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your good intention with a true vnderſtanding of his will; that ſo your commendable deſire of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; being accompanied with a right endeavour in the way, may carry you through this pilgrimage of ſorrowes, into the place of everlaſting joyes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
